Guide to the James R. Dumpson Papers circa 1922-2015 MS 3078
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Speeches, articles, papers, remarks, reviews, etc., 1932-2005; 2.5 Linear Feet
  - Speeches, articles, etc. (folder 2 of 2), circa 1964-1970 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Preparing Social Workers for Administrative Roles: An Overview of Curriculum Development in Social Work Education (undated).
    Report of Discussion Group A: "The Social Worker in Social Policy and Social Planning." International Conference on Social Work Education, Population, and Family Planning (Honolulu, 8-13 March 1970).
    Maternal and Child Health 4d: Welfare Programs and Their Relation to Public Health (1 May 1970).
    "Alcoholism in a Drinking Society": Teaching of Addictions in the Schools of Social Work (6 May 1970).
    Change: An Unending Need (Marymount College Convocation, 7 October 1970).
    Comments for the Symposium of St. Francis College: "Can Urban Public and Private Colleges Co-exist?" (8 December 1969).
    "The Place of Day Care in Meeting Children's Needs" (April 1964).
    Discussion Paper: "Present Day Trends and Future Developments in Education for Social Work" (18 October 1968).
    Human Rights and Child Welfare (Dallas, 25 May 1967).
    Human Rights and Social Welfare (St. Louis, 11 October 1968).
    "Ghettoes and Metropolitan Politics," by Robert C. Wood, Undersecretary of H.U.D., as discussed by James R. Dumpson (undated).
    Statement in Support of Higher Minimum Wage Legislation (undated).
    Presentation, Annual Scholarship Award Dinner, Mt. Zion Baptist Church (29 June [1968?]).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. [part 1], 1965 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Family Planning and the New York City Department of Welfare (21 January 1965).
    Notes for Conference on Group Care for Infants and Young Children (22 January 1965).
    Statement Submitted to Meeting of Advisory Council on Public Welfare of Department of Health, Education and Welfare (19 February 1965).
    Critique of Secretary of Labor Frank Zorilla's Paper (19 February 1965).
    The Who and Why of Poverty and the What of Its Elimination (1 March 1965).
    Community Development--Theory and Practice (Notes) (9 March 1965).
    Address at Marymount College Symposium--Christian Responsibility, etc. (13 March 1965).
    Volunteers in the Field of Public Welfare (31 March 1965).
    Remarks by JRD at Tesimonial Dinner in honor of Mrs. Mary Mass, Retiring President of CHILDVILLE (10 April 1965).
    Our Children--What Does the Future Hold[?] (13 April 1965).
    Notes for Panel on Anti-Poverty Program, Institute for Municipal Management (29 April 1965).
    A Short Look Back and a Long Look Forward (30 April 1965).
    Another Look at Public and Voluntary Agency Partnership (5 May 1965).
    The American Family--Image and Reality (13 May 1965).
  - Speeches, articles, etc. [part 2], 1965 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Our Welfare System--Radical Surgery Needed (8 June 1965).
    How High the Ceiling (13 June 1965).
    Problems of Public Policy Arising Out of Tax-Supported Family Planning Clinics (9 August 1965).
    The Role of Public Welfare in the Nation's War on Poverty (13 September 1965).
    Relationship of Voluntary Health Agencies to Official Health and Welfare Agencies (24 September 1965).
    Education for Public Welfare (23 October 1965).
    Address, James J. Hoey Award for Interracial Justice (31 October 1965).
    The Role of the Public and Voluntary Agency in Providing Services to Children (3 November 1965).
    Education for Public Welfare (1 December 1965).
  - Index to Speeches by James R. Dumpson, Commissioner of Welfare, 1958-1965 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1966 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    Toward the Development of Excellence (4 January 1966).
    Preparation and Presentation of the Welfare Budget (5 January 1966).
    The Relationship and Impact of Institutions on the Target Population (22 February 1966).
    Implications of the Poverty War on the Social Work Profession (16 February 1966).
    Implications of the Poverty War on the Social Work Profession (25 February 1966).
    Statement for Panel on Professional Consensus (5 May 1966).
    Draft statement to Subcommittee on Manpower, Employment and Poverty of Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare in re: S2993 (June 1966).
    Meeting Human Need -- The Required Partnership (19 June 1966).
    Social Work Education and School-Agency Relationship (20 October 1966).
    Present Issues in Family Planning (30 November 1966).
    Comments for Session on "Public Welfare and Its Alternatives" (6 December 1966).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1967 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    Effects of a Federally Guaranteed Income on Public Welfare (12 January 1967).
    Statement before the City Council, on the Organization of the Human Resources Administration (27 January 1967).
    Special Legislation and Human Dignity (16 March 1967).
    Hope for the Poverty Family (11 May 1967).
    A Challenge to the Children's Village (11 May 1967).
    Discussant's Remarks (26 August 1967).
    Address, 66th Annual New Jersey State Welfare Conference (3 October 1967).
    Breaking the Barriers to Self-Esteem for Millions of Americans (1967?).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1968 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Francis Cardinal Spellman and Charities (22 February 1968).
    Implementation of the 1967 Amendments to the Social Security Act (unedited draft; 24 April 1968).
    Public Welfare and Implementation of the 1967 Social Security Amendments (July 1968).
    Comments, Jewish Guild for the Blind Symposium (26 September 1968).
    Human Rights and Social Welfare (11 October 1968).
    Present Day Trends and Future Developments in Education for Social Work (18 October 1968).
    Social Welfare Education in a University: Its Objectives and Implementation (31 October 1968).
    Removing the Barriers to Self-Esteem (13 November 1968).
    Ghettoes and Metropolitan Politics (National Conference on Social Welfare, San Francisco, [1968?]; paper by Robert C. Wood, Undersecretary of H.U.D., as discussed by James R. Dumpson).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1969 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
    Statement to the New York City Council, Committee on Study of H.R.A. (18 March 1969).
    New Developments in Social Work Education at Fordham University (24 March 1969).
    Maintaining the City's Poor (5 May 1969).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1970 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Welfare and Income (with Paul Schreiber) (1970).
    The Social Worker in Social Policy and Social Planning (8-13 March 1970).
    Syracuse University Project, School of Social Work. V A Curriculum Building Workshop (27 April 1970).
    Alcoholism in a Drinking Society: Teaching of Addictions in the Schools of Social Work (6 May 1970).
    Change: An Unending Need (7 October 1970).
    Remarks, dedication of William H. Wheelock Boy's Group Residence, Children's Aid Society of New York (28 October 1970).
    Report to Unitarian Universalist Service Committee on Consultation Visit to Ban Co Center, Saigon, Vietnam (November 1970).
    Keynote address, New York State Welfare Conference (1 December 1970).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1971 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
    Keynote address, Central Region Conference, Child Welfare League of America (31 March 1971).
    Address, School of Social Work, West Virginia University (30 April 1971).
    Opening address, Ladies of Charity, Diocese of Albany, Northeastern Regional Conference (18 October 1971).
    Utilization of Data and Research Findings in Social Welfare Planning and Policy, International Symposium on Social Welfare Research (Washington, D.C., [1971?]).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1972 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    An Adequate Welfare Program! (January 1972).
    Breaking the Barriers to an Open Society (28 May 1972).
    Untitled remarks in "Social Conscience, the Citizen, and His Government: A Report on the Centennial Conference of the State Communities Aid Association" (22-23 June 1972).
    Issues in Social Planning for the Physically and Mentally Disabled (20-24 August 1972).
    Address, convocation of Hunter College in recognition of Mr. Fairleigh Dickenson (7 December 1972).
    Breaking the Barriers to an Open Society (1972).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1973 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    Statement of Dr. James Dumpson and Mr. Wells Klein on Child Welfare Problems in South Vietnam Before Hearing Held by the Judiciary Subcommittee on Refugees (11 May 1973).
    Statement... Before Sub-Committee on Labor, Health, Education and Welfare of the Committee on Appropriatons, United States House of Representatives (17 May 1973).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1974 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
    Closing dinner address, Conference on Children's Rights (4 April 1974).
    Speech to National Associaiton of Community Developers (8 April 1974).
    Statement... before Sub-Committee on Labor, Health, Education and Welfare of the Committee on Appropriations, United States House of Representatives (9 May 1974).
    Statement... before the Committee on Finance of the City Council, Executive Session (6 June 1974).
    In Memory of Elinor Gordon (13 September 1974).
    Transcription of taped conversation between James Dumpson and Mary L. Gottesfeld, editor, Clinical Social Work Journal (28 October 1974).
    The Realities of Welfare (15 November 1974).
    Speech for Annual Men's Day, Newman Memorial United Methodist Church, Brooklyn, New York (17 November 1974).
    [Remarks] Harlem Interfaith Board Meeting (22 November 1974).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    Welfare Reform and a Guaranteed Income (18 April 1975).
    Draft, introduction to Linkage Study (6 May 1975).
    Response... to Presidential Address: "Health as a Right: The Human and Political Dimensions" (11 May 1975).
    Age-In-Action (28 May 1975).
    Testimony on SSI (11 June 1975).
    The Effects of Budget Cuts on Services to Youth in New York City (19 June 1975).
    Testimony... Before New York State Department of Social Services Public Hearings on New York State's Proposed Annual Comprehensive Services Plan in New York City (31 July 1975).
    Blacks and the Welfare System (for Amsterdam News, 31 October 1975).
    Immigrants Among Us -- Whose Welfare is at Stake (7 November 1975).
    Testimony... Before the Subcommittee on Agricultural Research and General Legislation of the Senate Committee on Agriculture and Forestry (28 November 1975).
    Opening remarks... Conference on Treatment of Violent-Prone Adolescents (11 December 1975).
    James Cavanagh / James Dumpson Dinner by Chinese-American Democratic Association (23 December 1975).
    [remarks] At Abe Lavene's Farewell Dinner, Albany, N.Y. (1975?).
    Fund Raising in the Black Community [book review] (1975).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1976 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
    Response to the 1/15/76 Channel 13 interview of State Commissioner Stephen Berger Re: Administration of Public Welfare in N.Y.C. (16 January 1976).
    Social Welfare and Social Justice (30 March 1976).
    A Caring Society: Its Relation to Social Work Education (23 April 1976).
    Changing Concepts in Mental Health: A Thirty Year View (7 May 1976).
    Testimony... Before the Ways & Means Committee Subcommittee on Public Assistance, U.S. House of Representatives (11 June 1976).
    Communication as a Means for Equal Opportunity (July 1976).
    Response... to the final draft, "Training for Social Services in Public Welfare Agencies and the Role of Institutiions of Higher Education" (24 September 1976).
    In Memory of Shad Polier (October 1976).
    Title XX -- Present and Future for Families (17 November 1976).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1977 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
    [Speech to Rotary Club of Karachi, published in Karachi Rotarian, no. 28] (14 February 1977).
    Comments to NASW Meeting in Phoenix, Arizona (25 February 1977).
    JRD Opening Statement, CSWE (March 1977).
    Critical Issues in Social Work Education (April 1977).
    Social Welfare and Social Justice (13 April 1977).
    Restructuring the Delivery of Social Services in New York City (August 1977).
    Challenges to Social Work Education: Old and New (12 October 1977).
    Preparing Social Workers for Administrative Roles: An Overview of Curriculum Development in Social Work Education (20 October 1977).
    Options for Change (27 October 1977).
    Statement, Association of Black Social Workers Tenth Anniversary Dinner (2 December 1977).
    Welfare Reform: Work, the Incentives to Work, and Jobs (1977?).
    The Social Worker Views the Criminal Justice System, co-written with Michael J. Dowling (1977?).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    Issues in Social Work Education (20 April 1978).
    Shifting Responsibilities in the Field of Human Services (2 June 1978).
    Notes for Mental Health Center Symposium (15 September 1978).
    Administration of a Public Social Service Agency: A Retrospection Five Years Later (16 February 1979).
    The Future Relationship Between Publicly Funded Social Services and Income Support Programs, co-written with Arnold Gurin (April 1979).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1980-1989 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    Summary and Review of the XXth International Conference on Social Welfare (1981).
    Social Development in Times of Economic Uncertainty (Conference Working Document, 1981).
    For the Memorial Services of Richard Lodge (9 March 1981).
    Add Life to Years (Symposium on Healthy Aging, 7 April 1982).
    Statement in Favor [of] State Administration of Income Maintenance in New York State (27 January 1986).
    Intergenerational Programs in New York City, introduction (December 1988).
    Human Resource Administration Advisory Board Conference on the Homeless (23 May 1989).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    Towards a Caring Society in the 1990s (9 May 1991).
    Transcript of Dumpson's inteverview conducted by Noel A. Cazenave, Associate Professor, University of Connecticut, College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, Department of Sociology (May 1992).
    Hunter College Commencement Address (3 June 1992).
    Notes... for Citizens Union Foundation, New School's Graduate School of Management and Urban Policy, New York City Forum (20 October 1992).
    New York Medical College Inauguration of Rev. Harry C. Barrett (2 December 1992).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1993 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    Culturally Competent Mental Health Care (Remarks by Billy E. Jones, Health Care Delivery to African Americans, South Carolina Department of Mental Health, 22 January 1993).
    Dinner for Ruth Messinger at Hunter College (27 January 1993).
    Achieving Diversity: Taking Stock and Looking Forward (1 March 1993).
    JRD's Statement, Queens Hospital Center (9 March 1993).
    James R. Dumpson Acceptance Statement of the Frederick Douglass Award, New York Urban League (6 May 1993).
    [Speech in Cyrillic] (7 December 1993).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1994 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    Reforming Welfare: Putting People to Work (1994).
    HRA DSS Advisory, Annual Spring Conference, "Have We Learned From the Past?" (Meeting transcript, 14 June 1994).
    Notes for panel presentation on violence (5 October 1994).
    Minority Elderly, 1995 White House Conference on Aging (17 November 1994).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1995 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    Potential Impact of the Personal Responsibility Act on Senior Citizens in New York City (April? 1995).
    James S. Jackson, "Aging and the Life-Course Among African Americans" (April 1995).
    Comments: Columbia University School of Social Work Alumni Conference (19 April 1995).
    Comments Presenting Dr. Mary Ann Quaranta as Recipient of NASW NYC-PACE Award (27 April 1995).
    The Issue of Privatization Contrasted to Government Provision of Health Care: The New York City Case Study (notes for St. Petersburg Panel, AIHA Conference, October 1995).
    Black Family Task Force (November 1995).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 1996-1998 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    Creating a Caring Society for Children (1996?).
    Staff Observations for Community Foundation Panel (8 September 1997).
    Panel discussion, 30th Anniversary Conference, Northside Center for Child Development (1997?).
    Child Welfare--A Vision (1998).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., 2000-2005 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    Now That I Am Older (6 June 2000).
    JRD Notes for International Day of Older Person (5 October 2000).
    Remarks introducing Nina Bernstein for the National Resource Center for Foster Care and Permanency Planning at Hunter College School of Social Work (3 December 2001).
    Social Work Practice: Its Evolution and Application in the Current Environment (2003?).
    Statement of welcome, JRD Chair in Welfare Studies Colloquium on Traumatized Children in Child Welfare (16 April 2004).
    Remarks, National Association of Social Workers (11 May 2005).
    Statement, Forham University Commencement (2005).
    Helping Traumatized Youth in Child Welfare: Perspectives of Mental Health and Children's Services Practitioners (2005?).
  - Speeches, articles, etc., undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1930-2008; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Although correspondence may be found throughout much of the collection—see, for instance, Dumpson's personal letters from Pakistan (1953) in Series VI (box 8, folder 6)—the present series gathers only those letters that were specifically filed as such. That Series II spans seventy-eight years (1930–2008) in just nine folders gives some idea of the spottiness of the correspondence. Of historical interest are the letters Dumpson received in January 1965 during his tenure as New York City's Commissioner of Welfare, when social workers of his department staged a month-long strike for better pay and more manageable caseloads (see box 3, folder 15).
  Series II is sorted chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1930-1935 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1959 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    See also box 8, folder 6, for personal letters from Pakistan dated 1953.
  - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (letters re: Beame's appointment of Dumpson as HRD Administrator), 1961-1985 (bulk, 1974) (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (letters re: Welfare Strike), 1965 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1979 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1992-2008 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
- Series III. Memorabilia and Scrapbooks, 1928-2009; 1.5 Linear Feet
  Before its arrival at the New-York Historical Society, a portion of the Dumpson collection was grouped into binders (probably by someone other than James R. Dumpson) and labeled "Memorabilia I," Memorabilia II," etc., through "Memorabilia VIII," but skipping "Memorabilia VII." Two additional binders were simply marked "Memorabilia" without numerical designations. There is little difference between this "memorabilia" (now rehoused in folders) and the material found in the collection's scrapbooks, which contain a mixture of ephemera, correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, and publications documenting Dumpson's educational, professional, and personal life. Researchers should also consult the loose files and miscellaneous binders of Series VII for additional items in this same broad category.
  Series III is divided by format--Memorabilia and Scrapbooks--and sorted in rough chronological order.
  - Memorabilia I, II, III, circa 1954-2009 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia IV, VI (2 folders), circa 1964-2006 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Memorabilia, circa 1965-1970 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia, circa 1973-1987 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia V, circa 1987-1992 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia VIII, circa 1991-1993 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook. School records, 1927-1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1928-1930 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook. Cheyney State Teachers College, 1930-1932 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1931-1935 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1932-1941 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1948 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook, 1948-1955 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1948-1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    Contents in reverse chronological order.
  - Scrapbook, 1952-1958 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1953-1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes photographs and ephemera of James R. Dumpson's time in Pakistan.
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1964 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1975 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
- Series IV. Personal, 1950s-2012; 0.5 Linear Feet
  A small amount of personal material found scattered throughout the collection. Of chief interest are the photographs of Dumpson (box 5, folder 7), either alone, or posed with New York City officials or other dignitaries, both casually and at award ceremonies.
  Series IV is sorted in rough chronological order.
  - Personal. Press photos, circa 1950s-2008 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Personal. Award, blue ribbon, circa 1965 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    Approximately 100-inch (or 8.33-foot) blue ribbon "To Comm. James R. Dumpson," with hundreds of typed names. Likely presented to Dumpson on his 1965 resignation as New York City Welfare Commissioner.
  - Personal. Cards and programs, 1968-2012 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - Personal. 1270 Fifth Avenue theft, 1980 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
    Four-page itemized inventory of "articles stolen from Apt. 15N, 1270 Fifth Avenue, Manhattan," between September 5-8, 1980.
  - Personal. 1270 Fifth Avenue Cooperative, Inc. Board Minutes, 2007 July 10 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
  - Personal. Financial, 1984-1986 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
  - Personal. Financial (2 folders), circa 2006-2007 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13-14)
  - Personal. Award, "Spirit of Life", 1992 April 24 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
    State of New York "Legislative Resolution honoring Dr. James R. Dumpson upon the occasion of his designation as recipient of the 'Spirit of Life' Award."
  - Personal. "Hanging By a Thread: Gonna Make Me a Quilt" (Jeree Wade thesis), 1995 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
  - Personal. P.C. [Personal Computer] Info and Brother Fax Machine, circa 1997-2007 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
  - Personal. Medical insurance, 2006-2008 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
  - Personal. Poems by David Walker, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
- Series V. Fordham University, 1965-1996; 1 Linear Feet
  Series V holds a mixture of correspondence, administrative memos, and accreditation reports. Dumpson served as Dean and Professor of Fordham University's Graduate School of Social Service, 1967–1974. The school named a chair in his honor—the James R. Dumpson Chair in Child Welfare Services—in 1980. In 1994 the Fordham University Library Archives made available a 13-box collection of Dumpson's papers; see the finding aid in box 6, folder 14.
  Series V is sorted chronologically.
  - Fordham University [binder] (2 folders), 1965-1982 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Fordham University [binder], 1971-2002 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
  - Fordham University, 1972-1997 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fordham University, Report to Commission on Accreditation, 1974 March (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Fordham University, Dumpson Chair (4 folders), 1980-1996 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6-9)
  - Fordham University, Dumpson Chair, correspondence, 1981 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)